I remember the magic spell
From back when a rainbow stretched across the sky
In an instant, every corner of the world
Took on a brilliant hue
The voice of my heart
Always illuminates the path I need to take
It is because I doubt everything
That I know it to be true
Why does my heart still beat?
Why do my lungs still breathe?
Why is my chest burning with passion?
There's a reason for all of that
And, like the starry sky hidden behind the clouds
Like the ticket to a destination I lost somewhere
Like the history of the world from before I was born
You hold the answer just beyond my reach
If nothing else, I know that all too well
If nobody else, I know that all too well
（桐山 零(きりやま れい)）ん… あ…
まぶしい…
So bright...
I really need to get curtains.
いいかげん カーテン買わんと…
から揚げ… 最後の１個
The last piece of fried chicken...
Today's match is in the sixth block of the Lion King Tournament.
（零）今日の対局は
獅子(しし)王戦の６組トーナメント
相手は 二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)
My opponent is Nikaidou Harunobu.
もうすぐ夏休みか
It's almost summer vacation.
（零）プロになってからは
今日が初対局だ
This is my first match against him after turning pro.
Harunobu
When summer vacation hits, shogi tournaments for children are held on the roof of a department store.
夏休みになると—
デパートの屋上などで
毎年 子供将棋大会が催された
奨励会に入る前
全国の強い子供たちは
Before joining the federation,
talented kids from around the country participate in a number of small tournaments like this.
こういった小さな大会で
何度も顔を合わせる
Harunobu and I were regulars at those events, so we'd already met many times.
晴信も僕も そういうイベントでは
常連になっていて—
すでに何度も顔を合わせていた
あれは何年生の頃だったろう…
What grade was I in at that time?
It was terribly hot that day,
and I was facing Harunobu in the semifinals.
恐ろしく暑いイベントで
僕と晴信は
準決勝で顔を合わせた
その日は ほんとにひどい暑さで…
It really was hellishly hot.
He couldn't handle the heat well,
and his face was so flushed he looked like a red ogre.
暑いのが苦手な彼は
赤鬼のように真っ赤っかで
He seemed like he was in pain.
ひどく つらそうで…
Looking at him made me feel terrible as well.
（零）見ているこっちまで
苦しくなった
午後になると風がやみ—
In the afternoon, the wind died down and the temperature kept climbing.
気温はますます上がって—
I think he was anemic.
たぶん貧血を起こしているのだろう
His face was getting paler by the minute.
彼の顔は
どんどん青白くなっていった
Maybe it was an arrogant thought,
（零）傲慢な考えかもしれない
（零）でも僕は—
but I was looking for the quickest way to checkmate him.
何とか最短で
詰みまで持っていく道を探していた
I thought I should get the boy sitting in front of me into a cool,
air-conditioned room as soon as possible.
一刻も早く 目の前の子を
冷房の効いた涼しい場所で
休ませねばと思ったのだ
However...
しかし…
in the end game, as his imminent defeat became clear,
彼は負けが濃くなった終盤—
he recruited every piece he had into his army and began a desperate act of resistance.
ありったけの持ち駒を
自陣に投入して
必死の抵抗を始めたのだ
汗まみれの
真っ青な顔からは
A silent scream escaped out of his sweaty, pale face.
声にならない叫びが
漏れだしていた
I don't want to lose.
（二海堂）負けたくない…
負けたくない…
I don't want to lose.
負けたくない
負けたくない！
In that moment, I was ashamed of my arrogance.
（零）その瞬間
僕は自分の思い上がりを恥じた
I don't want to lose!
（二海堂）負けたくないっ！
The human sitting in front of me, drenched in sweat and reeling from the sun, was here because he wanted to win.
（零）目の前の人間が
こんなに汗まみれで
I don't want to lose!
フラフラになってまで
ここに座っているのは
（零）勝ちたいからなのだ
（零）
それはもう どうしようもなく…
But there was nothing he could do.
Just like for me,
僕と同じに
長い戦いになった
it was going to be a long battle.
もう僕の勝ちだった
The victory was already mine.
But he struggled on, one move at a time, searching for a path that wasn't there.
それでも彼は 一手一手
もがくように
見えない道を探して 指し続ける
However, he finally ran out of moves.
しかし ついに指す手が
無くなる時がきた
どんなに目を凝らしても
No matter how closely he looked,
there was no way for his king to survive.
もう どこにも
自分の玉の生きる道がない
I lost.
（二海堂）負けました…
After muttering that, he began to shed great big tears, like in a manga.
（零）そう つぶやくと彼は—
漫画みたいな大粒の涙を
ポロポロとこぼし始めた
僕はそれを せみの声と
デパートの屋上のＢＧＭの中で
Amid the crying of the cicadas and the department store's background music,
ただ黙って見つめていた
I silently gazed at him.
It would be the face I'd probably be sitting across for decades to come.
たぶん この先
何十年も向き合うかもしれない—
その顔を…
（零）プロになるということは—
Becoming a pro...
is like jumping onto a moving train that doesn't stop.
止まらない列車に
飛び乗るようなものだ
You can never get off of it.
もう二度と
降りることはできない
負けて転がり落ちるまでは…
Not until you lose and fall off.
In this small universe,
この小さな宇宙の中で—
it's an endless cycle of victory and defeat until you start losing your mind as you gasp, "I don't want to lose."
気が遠くなるほどの
勝ったり負けたりを繰り返すのだ
“負けたくない”と あえぎながら
Hey, Kiriyama.
（三角(みすみ)龍雪(たつゆき)）おう 桐山
Go take a peek.
ちょっと のぞいてみろ
Your rival is waiting for you with incredible vigor!
（松本(まつもと)一砂(いっさ)）お前のライバルが
すばらしい気迫で待ってるぞ
The calm mind
is the way
Boom
Chubby
Right?
His fighting spirit is so strong that
it's like an entirely different manga.
何かもう気合入りすぎて
ほぼ 別の漫画になってるだろ？
んにゃ 何つーの？　こう…
It's like, "Next chapter,
it's either checkmate or be checkmated!"
“次号 詰むや詰まざるや”
…みたいな？
I envy you, Kiriyama!
うらやましいな 桐山
Excitement
Look at that fighting spirit. That's all for you.
見ろよ あの気迫
Excitement
全て お前のためなんだぜ
He said he was your lifelong rival!
“終生のライバルだ”って
言ってたぜ　彼
Excitement
（零）落ち着け
Calm down.
まず ゆっくり息を吸い込む
First, breathe in slowly.
浅い息は視界を狭くする
Shallow breaths will narrow my field of vision.
Chubby
*(Actually Grin)
You're late, Kiriyama! I got tired of waiting for you.
遅いぞ 桐山
待ちくたびれたぞ
Chubby
*(Actually Grin)
（零）僕は時間どおりに来ました
I came at the appointed time.
早く来たのは
二海堂さんの方でしょ？　もぉ…
You're the one who arrived early. Jeez.
Right. I guess my enthusiasm got the better of me.
（二海堂）そっか！ うむ…
気持ちがはやってしまってな
さあ…
Okay.
始めようじゃないか！
Shall we begin?
（零）２五桂(けい)…　来た！
N-2e.
There it is.
S-2d.
２四銀
P-3e.
３五歩
同銀
Sx3e.
１五歩
P-1e.
He's gotten better.
強くなっている
He's slowly but steadily attacking me.
じわじわと
でも 揺るがずに攻めてくる
駄目だ…
No good. I won't get anywhere by just being on the defensive.
受けてばかりでは らちが明かない
I have to change the flow.
流れを変える！
（零）は… 汗？
Sweat...
It's just like that time.
あの時と同じだ
He looks pale.
顔色が悪い
二海堂の様子がおかしい
Something's wrong with Nikaidou.
Excuse me, but is the air conditioning working?
すいません
空調 効いてますか？
I'm sorry.
（記録係）あ… すいません
It seems to be on the fritz lately.
どうもエアコンの調子が
良くないみたいで
It's okay, Kiriyama!
（二海堂）いいよ　桐山
It's practically Heaven compared to the roof of that department store.
あのデパートの屋上に比べたら
天国だ
Let's continue!
続けようぜ！
L*5g.
He's coming in where I don't have pawns.
歩切れをついてきたか
Then I'll do this.
なら こうだ！
Px7f.
７六歩
What?!
６八銀？
S*6h?
Instead of capturing my gold, he dropped a silver?
金取りを放置して 銀打ち？
What?
何だ？
What is this?
何だ… これ？
Yeah.
負けたくない
I don't want to lose.
I don't want to lose either.
負けたくないよね
Calm down.
（零）落ち着け
Take deep breaths.
息は深く 視野は広く
Expand your field of vision.
As long as I keep my composure,
this board state should be in my favor.
冷静にさえいければ—
この局面
僕の方がいいはずなんだ
Calm down and keep playing.
落ち着いて 指し続けろ！
Shogi
Hall
The match continued until evening,
（零）対局は夜まで続き—
and I continued to shake off Harunobu's tenacious attacks.
僕は晴信の粘りを振り切り続けた
そして…
And then...
ありません…　負けました
I don't have a move.
I lost.
Oh, that's right. This face.
（零）ああ そうだ　この顔…
同じまんまだ　子供の頃と
It's the same face from when we were kids.
It hasn't changed at all.
ちっとも変わっていない
Nikaidou,
二海堂も　そしてきっと僕も
and most likely me too,
きっとこのまま ずっと ずっと—
will stay like this forever and ever and ever.
ずっと…
（花岡(はなおか)）晴信様
Master Harunobu.
お… 花岡？
Hanaoka?
グリーン休暇は？
世界一周はどうしたんだ？
What about your vacation?
What happened to traveling around the world?
I thought you weren't coming back for 80 days.
80日間
帰ってこないんじゃなかったのか？
I had your mother take my place.
（花岡）
大奥様に代わっていただきました
Thank you, Hanaoka!
Ten days was plenty for me,
and it was a very satisfying trip.
私は10日間で十分です
Are you sure it's okay?
船旅は満喫させていただきました
I'll be going, then!
To be honest, being separated from you
made me worry a lot, Master Harunobu.
正直 晴信様と離れている方が
心配で心配で…
I was in danger of having an arrhythmia.
もう不整脈とか起こしかねない
危なさでありましたよ
*Didn't freshen up
even slightly
You haven't gone to the hospital yet, right?
病院の方へ
行っていませんでしたね
Let's go see Dr. Morikawa right now.
このまま
森川先生のところへ行きましょう
I've already called him.
もう連絡はしてあります
（花岡）晴信様 おつらいですか？
Are you in pain, Master Harunobu?
また腎機能が
低下しているのでしょう
Your kidneys aren't functioning well again, are they?
（二海堂）すまない…
I'm sorry.
No, I'm sorry.
申し訳ありません
While I was gone, you probably weren't eating well.
私がいない間 食事も
むちゃなさったのでありましょう
（二海堂）
うぐっ…　すまない 花岡…
I'm sorry, Hanaoka.
いいんです　分かります
It's all right. I understand.
Subsisting on hospital food alone builds up stress.
病院食ばかりでは
ストレスがたまります
And it's been this way since you were a child.
それを子供の頃からです
I've seen how hard it's been for you all of these years.
どんなに おつらいか…
花岡はずっと見て参りました
But it's all right. I'm here for you now.
大丈夫　花岡がついております
Let's take our time and get your health back.
焦らず少しでも体調を戻しましょう
桐山様は…
対局はいかがでしたか？
And as for Kiriyama,
how did the match go?
I lost.
（二海堂）負けた…　強かった
He was too good.
I didn't know how good he'd gotten.
あんなに強くなってるなんて…
But...
でも…
I won't lose next time!
次は絶対に負けない！
Yes.
はい！
Of course, Master Harunobu.
もちろんですとも！　晴信様
Harunobu
Beyond the Night Sky
After my match with Nikaidou,
I went to their house as promised.
（零）二海堂との対局を終え—
約束どおり
僕はみんなのいる家に向かった
Come over again after your match.
（川本(かわもと)あかり）
対局が終わったら またおいで
That's the last day of Obon, so I'll make plenty of food.
送り盆なの　ごちそう作るから
（零）こんばんは　桐山です
Good evening. It's Kiriyama.
It's late. I bet you're tired.
（あかり）遅かったね　お疲れさま
おなか減ってるでしょ？　入って
You must be hungry. Come in.
Sorry it took so long.
（零）遅くなってすみません
（あかり）
ほら モモ　零ちゃん来たよ
Look, Momo. Rei is here.
I brought pudding.
（零）これ プリンです
（川本ひなた）さあ どうぞ！
Well, here you go.
I knew you'd be late, so I plated them separately for you.
桐山君のは
遅いから 別に盛っておいたよ
Downtown Specialty(?) Various Foods Triathlon
Thank you.
ありがとう
And I know you have a small appetite, so I made small portions.
桐山君 少食だから—
ちょっとずつ盛って
よけておいたよ
It all looks delicious.
（零）おいしそう！
But I'm not sure I can eat it all.
でも 食べきれるかしら？
And this is for Grandma and Mom.
（ひなた）で！ こっちが
おばあちゃんとお母さんの分です
I plated them using Momo's doll set.
モモのままごとセットに
盛りつけてみました！
Tiny...
Glare
What's that? What's that? I want it, I want it, I want it!
（零）おお… ちっちゃい…
Glare
It's so little...
（川本 相米二(そめじ)）
んあぁ…　さすがにもう
ビール２本はきついな
I guess two beers is too much for me.
うっこらしょっと
Oomph...
ふああ…
You can't sleep yet, Grandpa.
（あかり）
おじいちゃん 寝ちゃ駄目よ
そろそろ
送り火たかないと… だし
We have to light the ceremonial fire.
ああ もう９時過ぎか…
そうだな
It's already after nine? You're right.
If it's too late, Grandma and your mom will have a hard time getting back.
あんまり遅くなると
ばあさんたち 帰るの大変だからな
（零）ん？　この間 夕方たいて…
The other day, you lit the fire in the evening.
That's right. That was to welcome them home.
（あかり）そう！
この間は迎え盆だったから
We light that around dusk as if to say,
"Hurry home. We're all waiting for you."
迎えるときは—
早く来て
みんな待ってるよって
日が暮れる頃 たくの
But when they go back, we light the fire after dinner, saying, "We want you to stay as long as possible."
で 送るときは
少しでも長くいてほしいから—
晩ごはんが終わってから たくのよ
And when they come home,
we put out cucumber horses so they can get here faster.
でね
来るときは早く来てほしいから—
きゅうりの馬
But when they leave, we put out oxen made from eggplants
帰りはお土産たくさん持って
ゆっくり無事に帰れるように—
so they can make a slow and safe return, laden with the gifts we've given them.
なすで作った牛に
乗っていってもらうのよ
Well, shall we see them off?
さあ そろそろ
お見送りしましょうか
They were all smiling as usual,
（零）みんなは いつもと変わらず
にこにこしてるけど
but somehow a certain solemness permeated the mood.
やっぱり どこか けだるく
しんみりして見えた
こんなふうに
馬や牛を用意したり—
Seeing how they prepared horses and oxen,
ごちそうを用意したり
made a special feast,
and worried with everyone about welcoming and sending off the people who are no longer with us...
もう いない人たちの
来る時間や—
帰る時間を みんなで気にしたり
僕には—
It just made me think of a sad ceremony that only brings back painful memories.
余計 思い出して
悲しくなるための—
切ない儀式にしか思えなかった
Well, shall we go inside?
（あかり）さぁ そろそろ
うちに入りましょうか
Momo, let's take a bath and go to bed.
モモも お風呂入って寝よっかね
I'm gonna go to the convenience store.
（ひなた）あたし ちょっと…
コンビニ行ってくる
Hina?
（あかり）ヒナ…　今から？
Now? What are you going to buy?
何 買いに？
Um, a manga magazine.
えっとね… 漫画！
I forgot the new issue is out.
新刊 出てるの忘れてた
（相米二）坊主… ついてってくれ
Go with her, kid.
Huh?
Just get going.
（相米二）いいから早く！
（零）あ… はいっ
Okay.
She's walking fast.
（零）足… 速いな
どこ行くんだ？
そっちはコンビニじゃ…
Where's she going?
The convenience store isn't that way.
Hina—
ヒナ…
There she is.
（零）いた！
Mom!
お母さん！
お母さん
Mom!
ひっく… お母さぁぁん
お母さん…
I couldn't call out to her.
（零）声が掛けられなかった
Her voice caused a lump in my throat.
胸が詰まるような声だった
I'm sure she was holding it in when she was with everyone.
きっと みんなの前では
ずっと我慢してたのだろう
（ひなた）うあぁん…
（ひなた）ぐすっ…　うう…
Kiriyama...
桐山君…
ごめんなさい！　すぐ戻るから
I'm sorry...
I'll go back in a minute...
As I listened to her sobbing,
（零）泣きじゃくる
彼女の声を聞いていたら—
閉じ込めてあった疑問が—
the doubts I'd shut away began to seep back into my heart like ink.
胸の中で
インクみたいに にじみだした
That's okay.
いいよ…　いい
It's okay.
Let's stay here a little longer.
もうちょっと ここにいよう
うぅ… うっ…　うわぁん
For me...
（零）僕は…
For me, when I think about the real family I lost,
僕は ずっと消えてしまった
ほんとの僕の家族のことを—
I already gave up on crying because I thought it was pointless.
泣いてもしかたないから諦めて
It made me sad to think about them, so I tried not to.
悲しいから考えないようにして
I chased them out of my mind.
頭から追い出して 追い出して
I chased them out.
追い出して…
But...
でも…
was that really the right thing to do?
本当に それで
よかったんだろうか…
（ひなた）あぁーん　あああ…
あぁーん…
She's crying,
（零）泣いてる彼女と
泣かない僕と—
and I'm not.
But the two of us are gazing up at this beautiful,
二人並んで見上げる 美しい…
ただ ただ 美しい… ７月の夜空
simply beautiful, July night sky.
Beyond the Night Sky
Like a resplendent meteor shower
Your words enter my ears and catch fire
They come together like a school of fish
And form a warm corner in my once chilly bosom
As I stood in place, not knowing the right way to reach out
Your hand reached out to touch mine
And no matter how many nights may pass
That warmth still lingers and pulses within
Your very presence shines a bright light on every part of my life
Your racing heartbeat resonates with my frozen heart and sets it ablaze
Before long, the fire dies out
Leaving just one smoldering ember
Which remains with me and won't ever go away
Living inside of me in a place closest to my heart
Next Episode Preview
Episode 4
When you open it, it has to be like,
"Wow! That's so cute!"
（ひなた）開けた瞬間 こう…
ぱぁ〜って！ うわっ かわいい！
ってなるような
Hina is troubled by something.
（零）
ヒナちゃんは とっても悩んでいた
All right, little one.
I shall ask you your name.
（二海堂）よし！
小さき者よ　名を聞こう
What is it?
名を何と言う？
Bodoro!
（モモ）ボドロ〜！
（あかり）玉のように艶やかな
すばらしいお友達ね！
Your wonderful friend is just like
a nice and shiny round ball.
Sis, you picked up
someone else's kid again?!
（ひなた）
お姉ちゃん！ また よその子を？
Illustration: Noujou Jun'ichi
（二階堂）
３月のライオン
次回もお楽しみに！
Don't miss the next episode of
"March comes in like a lion."
Study shogi with me, everyone!
みんなも僕と一緒に
将棋を勉強しよう！